welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where equal hear and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
so as you know there's this virus out
there expanding pandemic and usually
with the pandemic you would try to catch
it early and you put a lot of work to
catch you early with tracing and testing
and isolating and we screwed that up we
didn't catch this one early and most
health professionals would have said and
did say well I guess it's gonna go
everywhere so I guess we should just try
to flatten the curve and deal with it as
best we can because we let it go and in
the last few weeks people have said no
no no you can't do that they need to
people will die which they will and
people have been really excited to try
to suppress to the lockdown and you know
people said stay home and don't go don't
go to work and many people have hoped
that that'll work and there is hope but
we should have a plan B because we are
really catching this late and all these
people who think yeah we can do this
they're the people who screwed up in the
first place so I'm not that hopeful but
of course we should try but the question
is what if we can't suppress it what if
it is basically eventually going to get
to most everyone what do we do then so
the usual story is to flatten the curve
and ie to spread out who gets infected
wins so that we aren't all expected at
the same time so that the medical system
will be there for us more so if we're
all infected in the same two weeks the
entire world then you know they just
can't help us all that's a bit of a
problem from the point of view of death
rates because in fact there is what's
called a dose effect that is when you
get sick with the virus you don't just
get sick or not you get sick with a
certain amount of virus and then initial
size of the dose that you get sick with
matters a lot so as soon as you get sick
with the virus your body turns on it
goes oh and that tries to grow a
response as fast as it can and the virus
is trying to grow as fast as you can and
your your body is in a content
growing but the size that initial amount
affects how well it can win so it's a
very tiny initial amount your body can
beat it out but if it's a much larger
amount and it that's worth so there's a
very consistent data in medicine that
the initial dose of a virus matters for
the severity the symptoms and whether
you die and we have data on that for
SARS which came out you know in the last
decade or two showing people in the
field when they were far away from a
source sources close to a source it was
three times the death rate when they
were closer to the source there's data
on measles in African villages where the
first kid and a family to get it would
have a 14 times lower death rate than
the other kids in a family who would get
it and we have this thing called
smallpox variations so back in the 1700s
before they have vaccines what they did
to treat smallpox around the world and
in the West starting then was to give
people a small amount of smallpox in
fact connection and then instead of say
a 20 to 30 percent death rate typically
for smallpox it would be a one to two
percent that's rate for smallpox and for
example at Valley Forge George
Washington inoculated his troops this
way and that put the deaths rate down to
2% instead of much higher which saves
Valley Ford and had the troops the US
troops in Canada the same thing a few
months earlier they would have not died
and we would eat part Canada would be
part of the United States that's the
history of the u.s. Civil War is it yeah
no the US Revolutionary War so that
means unfortunately that if we lock
everybody down and they catch the
disease at home they're gonna catch a
larger dose which means they have a
larger chance to die and that's a
problem with lockdown it doesn't mean it
isn't worth it if you could actually
suppress the whole thing and prevent
lots more people from catching it but if
we're in the situation where most
everything will get it then it's more of
a trade off roading lockdown
but it raises this possibility well what
if we could just deliberately infect
people small doses like they did with
smallpox
back in the 1700s for this disease so
that's not strange in theoretical I mean
we know how to infect people diseases I
mean often like you if you do an
experiment for say flu and you want to
get people infect with it so you just
make them play a card game where they
exchange the cards and then they quickly
all get infected by playing cards so the
idea here then would be to say well if
most everyone's gonna get it why don't
we try to intentionally get people to
get it with a small dose and in addition
if somebody's gonna get infected let's
isolate them because usually you use
isolation or quarantine resources to try
to isolate people most likely to get
infected soon but if you infect somebody
on purpose you know they've been
infected soon so let's create what I
call variolation villages or places
where you go you get infected with a
small dose Zulu lady that has according
to these previous reference points eight
three to thirty times lower death rate
from from this infection and they're
isolated until they're recovered and so
they don't infect other people and that
allows the spread out that's right the
medical demand overtime so that's not
everybody sick at the same time it
allows people to have this three to
thirty lower death rate it allows
critical workers to sort of you know get
certified early that that they've
recovered and then these safe to go to
the work into social contact that's the
generic idea here and that's what I've
been trying to get people to consider
and I think that's enough for my initial
presentation and we can go to Q&A
cool cool the discussion so for the the
people who just came in the chat he had
a question for Robin just right in the
chat box and then I'll call on you and
unmute you and you know mute yourself
and is asked Robin the question or if
you want me to read it on your behalf
just indicate down the chat box and I
might not we might not be able to get to
every question and I'm not gonna ask him
in order to and when used my discernment
about what has the best sort of flow to
it and I'll work Robin with a few
questions and before like inquiring into
the deliberate affection I'm curious
about bringing this to the personal I've
been talking to a lot of people about
the situation obviously
it's like emotional rollercoaster a lot
of people are going through wrestling
with this radical uncertainty so my
question for you is when did it dawn on
you that the situation was going to be
quite serious and how have you been
personally processing it moving my court
here we're just plugging in so losing
them on battery power that's just
checking their batteries should last for
a while I was tracking the news in
February and I think around February
12th I looked at my records and that's
when I said to myself in a tweet and
public I said oh my goodness this is not
being kept and move on
this is escaping Luhan to other Chinese
provinces in the rest of the world and
then in my simple-minded way I said
that's it that's it it's gone it's
escaped the initial place it'll go
through the whole world oh my god and
that's when I was starting to be very
concerned and tried to convince my wife
to sell stocks which I couldn't do and
that okay my Courtney's bugging me now
and so two days later I made my first
post on this topic because I was trying
to think about what we do and that and
so since then of course you know I was
very concerned for a while I like tried
to buy some stuff from trying to
convince my wife and other people it was
a problem and of course initially
everybody thought it was crazy because
they hadn't heard this from anybody else
so of course you know there's no point
in selling stock before everybody else
is gonna sell stocks right yes there is
but anyway and so you know but now I'm
I'm a professor so I can still work from
home and we don't have children at home
anymore so it's relatively easy for us
you know I'm not employed don't have
family around etc don't even have kids
at home but I feel for people who have a
lot more problems here right right
and then the other question I had is
kind of like how people's responses to
all these different kind of ideas and
suggestions right now
this is like provocative potentially
productive for a lot of people if they
hear this idea that you just presented
and even that that tweet you sent out
for the event like we got a few retweets
someone said the internet was a mistake
they should do this event in person so
you can practice what they preach stuff
and stuff like that
and I know you're no stranger to
controversy via misunderstanding
so do you have any sense of how this
type of stuff just the suggestion of it
could be presented without creating that
backlash against it I mean I just we
have to try so to explore different ways
of presenting it to different audiences
etcetera I don't there's no easy there's
no way to figure out ahead of time
before you go start and try so just
jumping in and try right great
it's just Robin Hanson technique just
just jump in and go for it yeah
so we tenured professors do have a
little safer if others if you feel a
little fire about being had this fold I
can appreciate that we have employers
who don't appreciate less things for
example right so let's turn to the Q&A
Jackson you have a question if you can
unmute yourself an accent Pasco - Robyn
yeah I actually I'm curious hey Robin
Jackson why has there been a difference
in the impact between
various viruses over the last 20 years
obviously the death rate and and the
virality but is it so say for example
SARS in early 2000s didn't really escape
much outside of Asia is it the nature of
the virus is this the nature of the
viruses just do vary a lot in their
nature you know there's some several I
mean they're complicated little things
they can be very different but the most
important ones here are safe four stars
others how what percentage of people are
killed there's how fast it kills them
and then especially whether they show
symptoms when they're infected all the
time so for SARS
as soon as people were infected they
showed symptoms and so that makes it
much easier to catch the infection as
soon as somebody has symptoms you
isolate them and check them and etc but
for this disease you can so you can be
sick for a week without showing symptoms
which means so you know lots of places
and affect on some other people before
you show sutures so that the impact here
is is almost entirely due to the nature
of the disease rather than the world
being different than right right I mean
we've we've had these sorts of diseases
for centuries of course and and our
world has changed but you know every
five years or so we have another thing
somewhat like this but you know they
vary in sort of how easy it is a
character like AIDS right HIV well you
know thanks contrary to fears that
doesn't be patched by handshaking or
coughing or you know touching doorknobs
etc you you have to be pretty close to
someone physically to catch aids right
HIV so this disease is relatively easy
to pass on in the air which is pretty
severe so because that means were around
each other a lot and we breathe around
each other a lot and that's why I'm ask
might be good idea so yes they differ
and how easy how they're caught how easy
their catch whether you show symptoms
when you're initially sick and you know
how fast you go severe and then what let
the chance of dying is there just a huge
range of these things cool there's a lot
of questions coming in Narayan
you had a few questions yeah I'm curious
about how much are coordinating with
others with this idea either to
satisfactory satisfactorily rule it out
as a good idea or or promote it as a
viable strategy to the world
I mean my part of the world maybe just
less organized than you hope I'm really
just one person and so I look at the
world and I figure out things that
seemed to make sense and then I try to
talk to the world and and react to the
world and have them talk to me so I'm by
now a 60 year old economist I've had a
long experience with having ideas that
seem to make sense and try to convince
the world mostly goes on ignoring ok
often I never know whether it was a good
idea because it's hard to get other
people to engage it I am puzzled here
about why the usual experts aren't
already all over this they already know
about the dose dependence of viruses
they already know about history small
parts why is it that I'm though I'm
talking about this that's just puzzling
to me but I do also know that often many
areas there's just people get stuck in
the way they think and an outsider can
sometimes see things that people don't
see on the inside but of course usually
in an outsider who thinks they see
something on the inside is wrong as the
insiders do those things but partly then
you need a conversation where the
insiders explain this is why you're
wrong
[Music]
do your sirens am i back in here yeah no
worries
um I was just I just want to reveal that
I'm asking because I'm part of a
coordination effort that involves a
bunch of people in the medical community
and I was thinking from my sides like is
there a way in which I can actually take
some of these ideas and help coordinate
this and how do I share this with this
community so the Stars wandering at
something they walk post I put up last
night and at the end that lists a bunch
of things you could do if you were
wanting to help in different kinds of
areas so one of the things is just
another medical literature research if
you have medical expertise and a bunch
of things there that you could do but
basically I'm just trying to get other
people to pay attention I presume that
if other people started to do more in
this I would suddenly be a small part of
this in the background because people
will be I'm just one person a lot where
people will be doing other things but at
the moment so I've looked out there and
I found five other people in the last
month - maybe voice similar ideas and
helped you know pocha them somewhere you
know pursuing it with some mild degree
but that's obviously not enough okay
Roku you just had a question yeah hi hi
Robin I mean basic basically my question
is just going over what you've already
said you know anything that you could do
with deliberate infection it seems to me
is is quite likely you could do better
with a vaccine and do you think people
have done a cost-benefit analysis on the
cost of letting people die versus the
cost of a vaccine that has some risks
associated with it versus the cost of
lock down because I did that calculation
just now and it seems to me that if say
half a million people die then the cost
of the lockdown for say six months would
be substantially bigger than than the
cost of those lives if you value them at
say five million each and the cost
presumably of a vaccine that's imperfect
would be even lower than the cost in
lives so regarding a vaccine
the usual conventional business which I
buy is that this is going to take at
least 18 months and perhaps several
years and perhaps never but it takes
that long because of the testing yes but
of course
you don't want to use one without
testing it because most of them are
don't work and some of them hurt so yes
we don't all don't want to be using a
vaccine until it's tested now there is
the claim which I find plausible that we
should be less shy about how we test
so typically we either test on some
other virus that's letting it but not as
definitely in this case or we test on
all population of people and then wait
to see which of them get infected and
then see how that helps them rather than
the more direct way of testing it which
is in fact some people right after you
gave them the vaccine and see if the
vaccine protected them now apparently
they're not doing that yet and that
would be faster but of course those
people would take more of a risk but it
certainly seems cost-effective to me
nobody doubts the cost-effectiveness of
that or that people would volunteer they
just think there's an ethical issue with
letting people volunteer to help save
millions of lives
which seems crazy to me but maybe you
are so but even with faster testing
basically there are many dozens of
vaccine proposals out there most likely
most of them don't work so a vaccine
searching isn't just like you do it and
it's not you you have to search in a
space of variations basically you're
taking the live virus and you're
changing it in a bunch of ways so that
it's not deadly but that maybe your body
would latch on to the same thing but
searching a lot of things to find out so
yeah I mean is it coming I I did
actually see some sorry sorry to
interrupt I did see some people who were
looking at synthetic RNA vaccines where
you actually you actually don't need to
use life vaccine but that's another
debate so I mean I guess my question was
just in the space of all possible
trade-offs you know is violation or
deliberate exposure really optimal
should we maybe just try to persuade the
vaccine people to do their thing much
more aggressively and just oh so they
they still say that even if you do it
more aggressively you're talking you
know at least six months here so in the
next month six months it seems likely
that maybe everybody would already be
infected you see by the time the vaccine
yeah
well this is doubling it was doubling
initially every week and now in some
places seem to be doubling every few
communal three days at that rate you
don't have six months that you talk
about trade offs the other trade-off is
between how hard to try to suppress how
hard to clamp down in order to prevent
growth and even suppress the virus and
as you know a lot of places have gone
harder on suppression in the last two
weeks but apparently not enough that is
even now on average most places are
still allowing the virus to grow not
shrink but just at a slower rate now as
long as we're doing that that gives us
more time to try to set up for your
variation if say this has peaked in the
within three weeks and the in three
weeks the entire world got it then maybe
I couldn't do anything to try to eat too
fast but if we're gonna try really hard
to suppress and we failed we might take
a couple months to fail and then maybe
you know give us a chance to do
something like this so you know in
general spreading out over time again
gives us each a chance to to have a
bigger slice of the medical system
devoted to us which is good on the other
hand isolating people means they have
more likely to get a high dose which is
bad so it's not clear whether that's the
trade-off okay let's go to Kaitlyn
Grimes you had a question yes I was
wondering like how do we choose who gets
infected so if the death rate is high
for elderly people and people with
underlying conditions then do we infect
them like would it be ethical to do that
or do we only infect people who are at a
low risk and then keep the two groups
separated so both in the last week I
realized there was this dose effect that
was really powerful and I've been
focused on that but in the previous
weeks I had just been focused on the
benefits of deliberate infection even
without this dose
where I calculated it was at least a 20%
reduction in deaths just using that and
a 20% for another thing so in that
analysis what I found that the optimal
thing to do was you know there's two
things you can do you can have isolation
or you just isolate people that you
don't affect them of course now they're
more protective and then you could also
deliberately infect people expose them
so in my analysis it was better to take
the young and healthy and deliberately
expose them and isolate the old and said
and that cut deaths 40% below randomly
doing no deliberate infection and just
screen in my solution so 40% I thought
was a lot of course now we're talking in
factor of 3 to 30 which is which is far
more bigger but even then I was thinking
of volunteers not where Zika so I was
thinking you play make a place where
people could go get infected and but
they would volunteer for it now if we
thought it was a good policy maybe we
all want to subsidize that and encourage
it sort of conquer the expenses maybe
adds a bonus maybe we'd want to do that
more for critical care workers like
medical workers people who work
electrical electrical systems things
like that but the idea was just to take
volunteers rather than force people and
ok sorry did you take into account
people who would accidentally get
infected anyway and still be
transmitting it within the community
well that's what's already happening so
that analysis was including that usual
effect of course adding this other
effect of assuming there's a rate at
which people are infecting each other
accidentally and now we add a place
where people can go and quarantine where
they have a small or a degree of
infecting each other because they're
more protected and then we use part of
that quarantine space to deliberately
infect people and then keep them
isolated there till they recovered and
that's the analysis that produced you
know 40% reduction in death rates ok I
see thank you ok
okay Siddarth you had a few questions
first I just wanted to start with so
whether if so let's say we consider
health care workers and for them this
might be the most bang for the buck
because they're the ones highest risk of
receiving high doses of the wider then
it seems that strategies which provide
sufficient personal protection to the
health care workers are successful in
Taiwan and Korea and Singapore so I
suspect that one counter-argument to
this proposal would be the we don't need
to do this risky thing we already have a
solution to protect these people we just
need to do it properly which we aren't
currently doing it so I was hearing
about what you thought about that well
so I'm not clear about what you're just
talking protecting the health care
workers themselves or the entire society
so if an entire society becomes infected
the health care workers are eventually
ending the effective cure themselves for
that so you might be talking about but
you could say Taiwan and Singapore and
South Korea have already so far seem to
successfully repress this why can't we
do that you know that's not what I was
asking because I know that they started
early and they started and they
certainly so I know that they weren't
there that that strategy is too late for
many countries all right what are the
very least it's not also even assuming
we could temporarily protect our health
care workers with some yeah not nothing
still we have the question of what about
the rest of us right if we're all gonna
get it up soon and we're all gonna get
it accidentally we're gonna suffer you
know the usual accidental death rate get
on this could we do better
sure yeah that's fair I just thought
that the gates of strongest to that kid
another question is it okay Peter if I
jump on it okay so I office on Twitter
but I'll just toss it again
in case your
you have some new thinking on this which
was that why hasn't this been done for
why this is other than smallpox and and
and one part that I had and here's what
you think about it is that it's just
really hard to isolate it was really
hard to isolate widel samples for
anything other than smallpox because
smallpox had the quote-unquote benefit
that there were scabs on your skin that
you could pick up and kind and sort of
store in a way that transports and keeps
for a long periods of time so but
portfolio it's not clear what you would
keep so I guess do you think that that's
possible leading that now we can
cultivate vital samples in the lab from
you know from infected people so perhaps
that objection doesn't really work so I
mean again I'm not an expert in this
area but my understanding is that over
the last century we've gotten used to
the vaccine solution and we think of
that as the advanced solution and this
variolation thing is the old-fashioned
thing that you used to do long before we
do how to do other thing and vaccines
are fine for a disease that's been
around for a while because you know the
two years it takes to develop one it's
not a problem
vaccines are only a problem for these
very new things and so far we basically
squashed all the new things relatively
quickly through you know trace except
for things like influenza where the
death rate was really relatively low and
so you know we weren't I guess they
weren't thinking about I don't know but
um I wish I knew why current you know
standard professionals aren't all over
this already
why they are talking about it why why
they're on reason but but I could
imagine that just so far they didn't
have to go there or they didn't feel
pressured to go there because their
other their toolkit need to work and
that this does feel and look bad people
that is infecting you with the actual
virus whether you have an actual chance
of dying
seems pretty old-fashioned than and mean
and you know crude what they had to do
in the old days but we modern people
shouldn't have to deal with that in one
final question in this
it's a croco brought up the question of
so let's say we remove barriers to
testing on white asses and allow the
participants of clinical trials to take
much higher risks than they currently do
then it seems possible that we might be
able to get a reasonably effective
reasonably safe vaccine within six
months and I think six months might also
be the time skill on which the video
Latian strategy would have to be tested
and tried in small-scale trials before
society would be willing in any sort of
way to accept it because I just think
yeah well so it's a big world
we're regarding the entire world's gonna
be affected by this so it's not just
United States so given how big and very
the world is I could certainly imagine
some part of the world trying this with
less solid pre-testing so again yeah
we're talking about people who are going
to get this anyway and so do you want to
try some way to get a smaller dose even
if it's not as solid a dataset as you
might get after a six month big study
it's not crazy there's somebody
somewhere in the world will think that's
worth the try
so it's not obvious to me that you'd
have to wait six months then again like
this is not simpler right we're just
gonna look it's ways to do smaller doses
basically but ways to have contact let's
say somebody you're sick in a smaller
dose there's just a lot of simple things
to experiment it's not that complicated
it's not like you have to do a lot of
necessarily chemical things or whatever
but again what I hear is that vaccines
will take a while even if we accelerate
the testing and and also just this is a
plan D I mean let's try to emphasize
that guinea pls pursue the vaccine yes I
don't mean it's a try for that but let's
set up a plan B let's at least be ready
to do something else that vaccines don't
come and even if it doesn't turn out to
be neither for this kind of thing you
know what this is not gonna be the last
pandemic this is in some sense a dress
rehearsal for something even bigger that
will come down the line that will matter
even more right so Amy you had a
question
yeah and my question is kind of related
to the idea of the places where this is
happening I live in New York City and I
mean even my video is not working but if
I showed you what I can see right now I
mean I don't think that this is going to
work here I think that for the most part
this is a in deliberate or non
deliberate infection that's going on
here so I'm wondering if a place like
New York City that is so dense and so
heavily populated so many people getting
infected so many more people are very
much likely to get infected will that
eventually become like a haven to do
trial of this type of deliberate
infections and I think at some point
it'll taper off just as it's getting
hotter in other parts of the country in
the world not clear how the level of
infection in area really affects
people's willingness to do trials about
this sort of thing there are several
conflicting factors and I don't see a
clear answer now it's clear that if you
if there's almost no threat of a problem
that people are and as the threat gets
larger they get more motivated to deal
something with something but then they
also just more scared and hunker down
and not being reflective or willing to
take chances and so and less able to
coordinate so it's not clear to me that
one year the peak of this that's the
time people would be willing to do
something organized together they might
be desperately willing to do something
personally but I'm less optimistic about
individual random people trying to
deliberately infect themselves more
optimistic about us organizing some way
to do that together by like doing some
trials and some collecting some data
public you know telling each other what
we've tried and then some so in my post
I'd talk about how you might have a
place like take an old hotel that at the
moment isn't being used or university
campus and bring people there all
together deliberately they look in fact
a whole cohort of people at the same
time then they can be there together and
socialize and interact
and and you with a large cohort you can
just try different variations in
different ways to infect them and
different apparently antivirals that can
slow the virus growth rate and you know
with even just a few thousand people you
could do a lot of experimentation and
find out what worked best but just
individuals who are scared hunkering
down and New York finally deciding they
want to do this on tomorrow because
they're scared I mean that might help
but I mean they're taking big chances
and it's going to be harder to collect
data out of that so the rest of us could
learn from it
Jake you had a question yeah thanks
Robin so my question is just about how
how high a percentage of compliance you
would need given that you're talking
about volunteers in order for it to be
effective at the kind of scale that you
wanted to and do you think that the
suspicion that you would have low
compliance in addition to the fact that
the optics of kind of coercing people
into doing this would be very bad given
that some some small percentage of
people are going to die do you think
that's why it's not being considered
more broadly that people just don't
assume that people be willing to infect
themselves when they have a kind of
last-ditch eye idea in their mind that
they wouldn't accidentally get infected
that they could comply with social
distancing measures and things like that
so you know I'm an economist and we
economist very much distinguish things
that you do that you benefit you
personally from things that we could do
together that benefits us collectively
even if some of us suffer personally and
obviously social distancing and other
sort of policies are presented and are
in many ways social policies that if we
if enough of us do it together we could
together get benefits and so if any one
person deviates by saying on social
distancing and the rest of us feel like
we should socially shame them and
discourage them in order to get the
collective to do what we all need this
is not a social collective policy this
is something that you can personally
benefit from possibly that is if there
is in fact a factor of 3 to 30 reduction
in your death rate because you get
deliberately in fact involuntarily
infected
that's something you might want to do
for your own personal benefit we don't
have to push you into that and then
there's no minimum threshold for being
effective the more people that do it the
better so it can just be a thing that we
put out there the main thing we need to
collectively do is to allow it to give
permission so we are so focused on
collectively preventing people from
hurting us all that we've set up a
system that actually makes it hard to
just do this now or at least it seems
hard so the first one of the first
priorities here just need to find a way
to get legal permission so that you
could just try to experiment with this
voluntary infection and you know then
you don't again you don't need the world
to agree with you you don't need
percentage of people to do it you just
do it then you get to that and and the
persuasive frame there is you can
control the amount of your dose which
you'd never be able to control in an
accidental context and therefore vastly
lower your risk of death right so you
show up to this what I call variolation
village and you know maybe there's a
cohort of a thousand people who all show
up this you know say it's a university
dorms or something you all show up at
the same time we're all immediately
isolated and immediately infected and
you know that that's when it's happening
and then as soon as you're all you know
verified to be affected you know either
individually or statistically based on
previous experience now if you can go
interact with each other and then some
people get sick but you'll all be we'll
all be watching out for that and once
you get sick we will take to a media
medical care that's available right
there and and then as soon as you know
you are completely recovered from this
they even that's when you can leave this
place and might just daggered classes
over a week or two and different people
left but you know it would have all
happened in this controlled context and
the rest of us can be assured you're not
infecting the rest of us if you're just
infecting yourself but not isolating
yourself then the rest of us shouldn't
be much more concerned about that and
much more reluctant to letting you do
that because then you're just speeding
up the whole pandemic when we were all
trying to slow it down Thanks
okay Brian you had a question Robin I
would like to hear your predictions or
the number of total cases and deaths by
the end of 2020
also your prediction for when
quarantines will be lifted and also how
bad you think the economy
so back in mid-february when I said oh
my god this is gonna wear everywhere and
other people thought that was kind of
silly I made a bunch of that's right
then so I think I made like 11 bets
about the following would the world have
more than 10 million deaths by 2022 that
is the end of the pom year and I got 11
people to give me 10 to 1 odds that that
was not going to happen but I still
think that's you know in the ballpark of
something impossible to happen I also
made some bets about whether 250,000
people in the US would die by that same
time and you know the current newspaper
today or yesterday said you know it
would be good outcome of only a hundred
thousand people died I think that means
they're admitting that it's not crazy
from 250,000 people yes so the economic
effect is a choice we have so you know
that's a choice about our policy
response I'm pretty clear that the
economic costs are high lock down is
expensive we are a rich world and we can
in some sense afford to pay a lot for
things but it will be expensive and the
key question is are we paying the right
amount for the right thing in some sense
the worst case is we pay an enormous
amount and we still don't keep it from
spreading and then we are hit with the
same massive death wave that we would
have a hit with anyway and you know then
that we don't do much about it through
variation or other means and you just
still have a peak where within the same
roughly month most of the people in an
area get sick
and then mostly they don't have much of
nautical care don't and we will either
just hit that in the next few weeks
because our methods are just not helping
or our methods will be helping in which
case they will slow it down and we will
hit a peak in the next few months or if
we're lucky and we will suppress it in
the next few weeks or months so that it
can be get smaller but I'll never go
down to zero and then we're faced with
repeatedly having to suppress it when it
pops back up again and doing that
indefinitely until it backseat shows up
and that could also fail in which case
you know we could even suppress it for
six months that great expense and then
it still pops up and takes over and we
still have all the same death okay no
I'm you had a question what some
countries like some countries do more
politically and legally amenable in the
United States or Canada or most Western
countries to a burial Asian village
experiment and under what circumstances
might the data gathered there be useful
to us I'm sure the data would be very
useful that is this this disease isn't
very different for different people in
the world at least that's the current
thinking there has been substantial
variation around the world and people
are puzzling over that and I think dos
attacks are one plausible contribution
to those big variations but I think an
experiment most anywhere would be
informative and of course the main
things would just be you find out well
what how do you deliver a small dose and
then what's the death rate associated
with that and then there's some other
questions like do you take it in your
mouth you take it you breathe that you
do it on the skin what will be the way
to deliver it and then there's like I
said antivirals that might in
conjunction also help and so just
whatever data they have on what people
tried and what the death rates were we'd
be great wherever they did it obviously
there are many places with a lot of
varying regulations and if it weren't
for the fact that it started in China I
might have said China in the East would
have been more open to this but of
course hardly what's going on to say
China and South Korea and Singapore
their story now is well we've kept it
out we don't need
else we're done rest the world
yes and until they face the threat that
this will in fact Sweetback one to them
that they can't and they can't keep it
out they probably wouldn't be interested
in variability until they actually felt
threatened which unfortunately they
probably eventually will be but then the
waiting for them to do that at that late
date may be kinda late perhaps a country
like Turkey or some semi-authoritarian
place I have no idea it's a random thing
I had a roaster Robin are you there
looks like your camera froze turkey will
say your camera froze there Robin we
missed the last three seconds of that
sorry Internet are you back you're back
now you're good good time okay I
realized if I need to change these yeah
okay so we got a question did it Dan
Feldman you have a question yeah well
what is your view on herd immunity and
how does it influence either plan a the
vaccine or Plan B the micro dosages with
isolation so herd immunity is what
happens when most of us get infected
and it's the thing that naturally stops
the whole process after that point if
we're trying to suppress he prevent most
people from getting infected then herd
immunity isn't is a little drawing for
we're going for suppression and many
people are hopeful about that and that's
the official focus a lot of policy is
the claim that we're going to suppress
I'm skeptical that we're going to
succeed but I'm happy to let us try at
least a modest cost
unless we suppress herd immunity is
basically what we're going for
it's basically most people enough people
get it so that you know there's not
enough people who in fact marking it's
just a name for the scenario where most
people get it so the disease can regrow
Peter can I ask one follow-up question
yep your solution if I'm getting this
correct it appears to be sort of a
playing on perhaps libertarian or
neoclassical sensibilities playing on
self-interest that if I get if I go to a
place and get microdose and get infected
and this protects me personally but it
also has this benefit and I'm not quite
exactly sure of the argument yet I that
this also benefits the collective and
I'm just wondering am i understanding
this correctly and if if I am
understanding this correctly do you see
this as you know given that we're still
operating in kind of a libertarian
neoliberal do clap neoclassical world
that this gives your idea a certain
advantage a stickiness that could take
hold in the culture I mean I have a PhD
in formal political theory I of course
you know know a lot of things about
politics and coordination and governance
but I don't really think this issue you
know is affected much by that stuff just
in general the world sometimes you know
we have problems where each person's not
themselves and that adds up to a fix for
everybody and sometimes we have
coordination problems which that doesn't
work for where we need to work together
to suppress individual incentives so
that we can produce
coordination is hard so there are many
coordination problems in the world that
we failed for today to achieve you know
global warming war innovation fisheries
etc and in many ways people think of
pandemic
as having big coordination problems
especially if they're trying to do a
suppression the social distancing et
cetera but this particular solution
happens not to need coordination which
is good because coordination started
regime that's not a statement about
libertarian policy or anything else it's
just the fact of the world you know
often the debates of governance is about
whether coordinate whether our
government systems are good enough to
achieve certain kinds of coordination or
not so some people might say look if
we're level we just can't cheat global
warming policy the world is in our
capable it's not for date sorry we're
just not going to do anything other
people might say no no we need to try
harder and pay more cost stronger
institutions coordinate that's a
standard debate and you know other
points happy to engage that and
participate there that's not issue here
I here the issue is we've set up
regulatory systems to prevent people
from hurting themselves with medicine
but that's getting in the way of this
way people that just help themselves if
only we allow it
okay so we'll have maybe two two more
questions Raven you have a question for
Robin yeah so let's say this proposal
would work how do you think that
people's like kind of intuitive or
perceived risk when thinking about this
proposal their cognitive biases would
play out in their reactions so both
experts but then also the general public
and also like purses a person's
perceived level of autonomy over
avoiding illness right now I'm not sure
risk and autonomy are the dominant
effects I mean I see that they are
effects but I'm not sure they're the
strongest one I would say that the
biggest one is just a sort of conformity
and authoritarianism that people have
with respect to medicine that is until
the medical authorities recommend
something they don't think anybody
should do it and that's here and of
course until other people are doing
korie's recommend many individual people
don't want to do something especially
regarding medical treatments or diseases
or something so it's long been observed
and it is true and you're seeing it now
that people who are very independent and
autonomous in times of peace and
prosperity when there is a big threat
like a war or a pandemic they suddenly
become much more conservative they
suddenly want to give government more
power they suddenly want to collective
have more power they want to repress
dissent repress deviation because
they're scared and they think we need to
all stick together with a common policy
to make things work and that's what
we're seeing now but unfortunately this
if the authorities endorse this and if
everybody else was doing it I think most
people go along just fine that's
certainly what we saw in 1700 so 1700 s
initially a lot of people thought
variolation was crazy and they highly
opposed to it's like the ancient actuals
today it will they keep but once the
authorities ignited most people were
doing it then most people did it and it
was it was a standard thing to do and
that's just more than dominant factor
here's about conformity and authority
and less about your personal calculation
of risk unfortunately yeah obviously
it's how you frame it right you could
think I'm gonna go in this place and I
might die sure but of course I'm gonna
stay out here and I might die you're
thinking about the difference between
not going in and going in that's a
different framing then thinking about
the absolute risk and then first we have
this framing about longer we let other
people take and so even today as other
would mentioned people have proposed
accelerated vaccine trials where people
are paid in order to get the actual
virus and then a vaccine and a lot of
people oppose that that's an ethical
issue for a lot of people even at the
moment and so this would bring up those
similar sort of ethical issues do we
allow people to voluntarily go in even
if they might get a lower dose so last
question let's go with Daniel Zev my
question is are you yourself going to
get deliberately infected and if not
like what would it take for you to do
that
somehow this is new to me okay this told
me I was muted per moment okay never
right there's there's two issues one do
I want to do something illegal or do I
want to stay within the legal framework
and try to to make something legal and
that we can do about work right and
another issue is do I want to do some
individual personal action with my own
little personal resources or do I want
to be part of some group or organization
that does things together so here my
main initial strategy has been to try to
do things legally together so if we
could set up a thing where people many
people together we're being deliberately
infected I certainly am open to being
part of that process I'm not going to
just go try to do it myself personally
by flying China or something but that
doesn't make much sense the the point is
to first of all you know do it enough
together that we can collect data
together about what works or not and I'm
you know willing to consider being part
of a trial but then of course you know
we want to do a trial with the people
who are the most apt appropriate for it
and like the data and you'd like some
medical professionals to be part of this
process to the set up how it happens and
set up how its traced and you know I
mostly now want to try to help us
together do this so I'm less focused on
me saving myself and more how could we
together create a process where we can
do this together I would hold out the
possibility that if we kept having legal
in permission and opposition or at least
ambiguity maybe some sort of civil
disobedience or group where it does it
anyway in defiance of perhaps rules but
even that I'd want to do it with other
people together where we had organized
it and we're trying to do it was
systematically sharing information now
to do it that's right thing all right
very cool so raven had a slogan do you
want to want to end it off
no she's legally together gray sloven
okay
so yeah we'll end it there Robin I'll
give it a 4/4 time
yeah yeah thank you everyone for coming
and thank you Robin do you have any
closing thoughts before I do some
closing announcements about myself no
you're all you know great then paying
attention taking seriously that I can't
ask any more great great so I'll make
some closing announcements in a moment
and Robin again thank you so much for
coming today thank you everyone for the
great questions we have a lot of cool
events coming up at the the stoah we
have some meditations breathwork even
existential dance parties Robin I'd love
for you to come to the next exit and
dance party I think that would be quite
a treat it's quite fun and then the
session we have tonight at 7:00 p.m.
Eastern Time is a stoical training
program so you can RSVP do that on the
website and that's WWE CA and the stoah
is running off a gift economy I'm
viewing this as a gift to the world and
this time of need if you're inspired to
provide a gift in return just go to the
website and the gift economy and there's
more information there alright everyone
thank you again thanks for anything
thanks Robin